<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Observations, both historical and moral, upon the burning of London, September 1666 with an account of the losses, and a most remarkable parallel between London and Mosco, both as to the plague and fire : also an essay touching the easterly-winde : vvritten by way of narrative, for satisfaction of the present and future ages / by Rege Sincera.</title>
            <author>Rege Sincera.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1667</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 53 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A53837</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing O92</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R1890</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12959282</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12959282</idno>
            <idno type="VID">96059</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A53837)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 96059)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 723:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Observations, both historical and moral, upon the burning of London, September 1666 with an account of the losses, and a most remarkable parallel between London and Mosco, both as to the plague and fire : also an essay touching the easterly-winde : vvritten by way of narrative, for satisfaction of the present and future ages / by Rege Sincera.</title>
                  <author>Rege Sincera.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 36 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Thomas Ratcliffe, and are to be sold by Robert Pawlet ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1667.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>London (England) --  Fire, 1666.</term>
               <term>Moscow (Russia) --  History.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:96059:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>OBSERVATIONS BOTH Hiſtorical and Moral UPON THE BURNING OF LONDON, <hi>September</hi> 1666.</p>
            <p>With an Account of the LOSSES.</p>
            <p>And a moſt remarkable Parallel between <hi>LONDON</hi> and <hi>MOSCO,</hi> both as to the PLAGUE and FIRE.</p>
            <p>Alſo an Eſſay touching the Eaſterly-Winde.</p>
            <p>VVritten by way of Narrative, for ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the preſent and future Ages.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Rege Sincera.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed by <hi>Thomas Ratcliffe,</hi> and are to be fold by <hi>Robert Pawlet</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> in <hi>Chancery-lane.</hi> 1667.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:96059:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:96059:2"/>
            <head>To his much honored and reſpected Friend JOHN BULLER <abbr>Eſq</abbr> A Worthy Member of the Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Houſe of COMMONS.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THis little Treatiſe having lyen dormant in a corner of my Desk ever ſince his Birth, (which was three weeks after the Fire) hath got at laſt ſo much ſtrength as to walk abroad. The reaſon of his long repoſe was, that I expected when ſome more pregnant Wit and better Pen would have undertaken this Taske, which is
<pb facs="tcp:96059:3"/>altogether out of my Profeſſion and Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment: But finding that hitherto all that hath been written concerning it, as to the Narrative of its beginning, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs and ending, hath been thought de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fective, I have given it leave to ſhew it ſelf abroad, with Obſervations there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, under Your Honorable Name, as well to avoid the malignancy of Cenſure, as to teſtifie unto the World how much I am</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your humble and affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onate Servant, <hi>Rege Sincera.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:96059:3"/>
            <head>Obſervations and Reflections, both Hiſtorical and Moral, upon the laſt lamentable FIRE that hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened in the famous CITY of <hi>LONDON,</hi> the Second Day of <hi>September, Anno 1666.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>BEfore we proceed any further in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination of ſo lamentable and diſmal a Subject, we have thought fitting, for the curioſity of thoſe that ſhall read theſe Lines, and for the ſatisfaction of Poſterity, in whoſe hands it may chance to come, to ſett down the true and naked Narrative of the Fact as it did happen, and as it hath been printed by the conſent of His Majeſty, and of the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Authority, that the Reader being made cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:96059:4"/>of the truth of the Accident, may the more willingly proceed to the Examination of thoſe Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations we have made upon it.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Whitehall, September <hi>8.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ON the Second inſtant, at one of the Clock in the morning, there happened to break out a ſad and deplorable Fire in <hi>Pudding-lane</hi> near <hi>New-Fiſhſtreet;</hi> which falling out at that hour of the night, and in a quarter of the Town (ſo cloſe built with Wooden pitched Houſes,) ſpread it ſelf ſo far before day, and with ſuch diſtraction to the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants and Neighbours, that care was not taken for the timely preventing the further diffuſion of it, by pulling down Houſes, as it ought to have been; ſo that this lamentable Fire in a ſhort time became too bigg to be maſtered by any Engines, or work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing near it. It fell out moſt unhappily too, that a violent Eaſterly winde fomented it, and kept it burning all that day, and the night following ſpread it ſelf up to <hi>Grace-church-ſtreet,</hi> and downwards from <hi>Canon-ſtreet</hi> to the Waterſide, as farr as the <hi>Three Cranes</hi> in the <hi>Vintrey.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The People in all parts about it, diſtracted by the vaſtneſs of it, and their particular care to carry a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way their Goods, many attempts were made to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:96059:4"/>the ſpreading of it, by pulling down Houſes, and making great Intervals, but all in vain, the Fire ſeiſing upon the Timber and Rubbiſh, and ſo conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing it ſelf even through thoſe ſpaces, and raging in a bright flame all Monday and Tueſday, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding His Majeſties own, and his Royal High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs indefatigable and perſonal pains to apply all poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible remedies to prevent it, calling upon and help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the People with their Guards, and a great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Nobility and Gentry unweariedly aſſiſting therein; for which they were requited with a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand bleſſings from the poor diſtreſſed People. By the favour of God the winde ſlackned a little on Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſday night, and the Flames meeting with Brick-buildings at the <hi>Temple,</hi> by little and little it was obſerved to loſe its force on that ſide, ſo that on Wedneſday morning we began to hope well, and his Royal Highneſs never deſpairing, or ſlackning his perſonal care, wrought ſo well that day, aſſiſted in ſome parts by the Lords of the Council before and behind it, that a ſtop was put to it at the <hi>Temple-Church,</hi> near <hi>Holborn-bridge, Pye-corner, Alderſgate, Cripple-gate,</hi> near the lower end of <hi>Coleman-ſtreet,</hi> at the end of <hi>Baſinghall-ſtreet,</hi> by the <hi>Poſtern,</hi> at the upper end of <hi>Biſhopſgate-ſtreet,</hi> and <hi>Leadenhall-ſtreet,</hi> at the <hi>Standard</hi> in <hi>Cornhill,</hi> at the Church in <hi>Fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>church-ſtreet,</hi> near <hi>Clothworkers-hall</hi> in <hi>Mincing-lane,</hi> at the middle of <hi>Mark-lane,</hi> and at the <hi>Tower-Dock.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>On Thurſday, by the bleſſing of God, it was whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:96059:5"/>beat down and extinguiſhed, but ſo as that Even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it unhappily broke out again at the <hi>Temple,</hi> by the falling of ſome ſparks (as is ſuppoſed) upon a pile of Wooden buildings, but His Royal High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, who watched there that whole night in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, by the great labours and diligence uſed, and eſpecially by their applying powder to blow up the Houſes about it, before day moſt happily maſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it.</p>
               <p>Divers Strangers, <hi>Dutch</hi> and <hi>French,</hi> were du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Fire apprehended, upon ſuſpition that they contributed moſt miſchievouſly to it, who were all impriſoned, and informations prepared to make a ſevere inquiſition thereupon by my Lord Chief Juſtice <hi>Keeling,</hi> aſſiſted by ſome of the Lords of the Privy-Council, and ſome principal Members of the City; notwithſtanding which ſuſpicions, the manner of the burning all along in a train, and ſo blown forwards in all its way by ſtrong windes, make us conclude the Whole was an effect of an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy Chance, or to ſpeak better, the heavy hand of God upon us for our Sinnes, ſhewing us the terror of his Judgements in thus raiſing the Fire; and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately after his miraculous, and never enough to be acknowledged mercy, in putting a ſtop to it when we were in the laſt deſpair, and that all at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts for the quenching it, however induſtriouſly purſued, ſeemed inſufficient. His Majeſty then ſate hourly in Councel, and in his own perſon making rounds about the City, in all parts of it
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:96059:5"/>where the danger and miſchief was greateſt, till next morning, that he hath ſent his Grace the Duke of <hi>Arbemarle,</hi> whom he called from Sea to aſſiſt him in this great occaſion, to put his happy and ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full hand to the finiſhing of this memorable Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance.</p>
               <p>About the <hi>Tower</hi> the ſeaſonable Orders given for plucking down Houſes to ſecure the Magazins of Powder was more eſpecially ſucceſsfull, that part be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up the winde; notwithſtanding which, it came almoſt to the very Gates of it, ſo as by this early proviſion the ſeveral Stores of Warr lodged in the <hi>Tower</hi> were entirely ſaved; and we have further this infinite cauſe, particularly to give God thanks, that the Fire did not happen in any of thoſe places where his Majeſties Naval-ſtores are kept; ſo though it hath pleaſed God to viſit us with his own hand, he hath not by diſ-furniſhing us with the means of carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on the Warr, ſubjected us unto all our Enemies.</p>
               <p>Through this ſad accident it is eaſie to be imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, how many Perſons were neceſſitated to remove themſelves and Goods into the open Fields, where they were forced to continue ſome time, which could not but work compaſſion in the Beholders. But His Majeſties care was moſt ſignal in this occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, who, beſides his perſonal pains, was frequent in conſulting alwayes for relieving thoſe diſtreſſed perſons; which produced ſo good effect, as well by His Majeſties Proclamations, and the Orders iſſued
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:96059:6"/>to the Neighbours Juſtices of Peace, to encourage the ſending in of Proviſion to the Markets, which are publickly known, as by other directions, that when His Majeſty fearing leſt other Orders might not yet have been ſufficient, had commanded the Victualer of his Navy to ſend Bread into <hi>Morefields</hi> for relief of the Poor, which for the more ſpeedy ſupply he ſent in Baskets out of the Sea-ſtores, it was found that the Markets had been already ſo well ſupplyed, that the People being unaccuſtomed to that kinde of Bread, declined it, and ſo it was return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in great part to His Majeſties Stores again, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any uſe made of it.</p>
               <p>And we cannot but obſerve, to the confutation of all His Majeſties Enemies, who endeavour to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade the World abroad of great Parties and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>affection at home againſt his Majeſties Government, that a greater inſtance of the affection of this City could never be given, than hath been now given in this ſad and deplorable accident, when, if at any time, diſorder might have been expected from the loſſes, diſtraction, and almoſt deſperation of ſome Perſons in their private Fortunes, thouſands of people not having to cover them. And yet in all this time, it hath been ſo farr from any appearance of Deſignes or Attempts againſt His Majeſties Government, His Majeſty and His Royal Brother out of their care to ſtop and prevent the Fire, frequently expoſing their Perſons with very ſmall Attendants in all parts of the Town, ſometimes even to be intermixed with
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:96059:6"/>thoſe who laboured in the Buſineſs, yet nevertheleſs there hath not been obſerved ſo much as a murmuring word to fall from any; but on the contrary, even thoſe Perſons whoſe Loſſes rendred their Condition moſt deſperate, and to be fit objects of their Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, beholding thoſe frequent inſtances of His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties care of His People, forgot their own miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and filled the Streets with their Prayers for His Majeſty, whoſe Trouble they ſeemed to compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionate before their own.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:96059:7"/>
               <head>Obſervations.</head>
               <p>THe Philoſophers, Rhetoricians and Lawyers do agree, that all the circumſtances of a fact, are happily contained in a <hi>Latine</hi> Verſe framed for that purpoſe, as well to illuſtrate the Method, which is the life of Hiſtory, as to help the Memory, which is to reap the benefit of it: the Verſe runneth thus;</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Quis, quid, ubi, quibus auxiliis, cur, quomodo, quando?</l>
                  <l>Who hath done it, what hath he done,</l>
                  <l>Where, by what means, wherefore, how, when?</l>
               </q>
               <p>Although theſe Disjunctives ſeem at firſt ſight to carry no great ſence, nevertheleſs when they ſhall be throughly examined it will be found, that they do contain all what can be ſaid upon a ſubject, and that out of them as out of ſo many living ſprings may be drawn all what is neceſſary for the clearing of a propounded Queſtion; and we will not be aſhamed in this to follow the method of the Schools and the authority of the learned, knowing that whatſoever fault ſhall be found in't, will rather be imputed to our incapacity then to the foundation we have built upon. Therefore to begin.</p>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:96059:7"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Quis?</hi> Who hath done it? <hi>SECT.</hi> I.</head>
                  <p>FOR the clearing of the darkneſs wherein the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane underſtanding is naturally wrapt up in diſtinguiſhing the ſeveral accidents and events that happen dayly in this ſublunary World. The Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers have eſtabliſhing two principal cauſes, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto every one may have his recourſe for his ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction and the ſecuring of himſelf, that nothing happeneth by chance, which is the opinion of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperate and Atheiſtical perſons. The firſt and univerſal cauſe is God Almighty, who as he alone hath created the World, ſo hath he alſo reſerved to himſelf alone the government thereof, inſomuch that the leaſt accidents that befall, depend meerly from his providence, neither is there any thing hidden to him with whom we have to do; it is he without whoſe leave and knowledge not a hair falleth from our heads, and who telleth us by his Prophet that <hi>There is no evil in the City but he hath done it.</hi> This is that firſt Cauſe which ought to captivate our underſtandings under its will, to make us admit all Events with an equal mind, and ſubmit our pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience to his diſpenſations, ſaying with <hi>David, I did hold my peace becauſe thou didſt it,</hi> Pſal. 50. verſ. 21. The other Cauſes are called Second cauſes, becauſe moſt commonly God maketh uſe of them for the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:96059:8"/>accompliſhing of his will, and theſe are divided into as many branches as there are individual creatures in the World. By theſe a man liveth, being begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by the ſeed of his parents; dieth being ſuffocated, falleth being drunk, is drowned in making ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrack, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Where it is to be obſerved that ſeveral ſecond Cauſes may concurr together to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction of one and the ſame effect; as in this ſad and lamentable Accident we ſee the careleſneſs of a <hi>Baker,</hi> the ſolitarineſs and darkneſs of the Night, the diſpoſition of old and ruinous Buildings, the narrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Streets, the abundance of combuſtible and Bituminous matter, the foregoing Summer extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary hot and dry, a violent Eaſtern Wind, and the want of Engines and Water, concurr as it were unanimouſly to the production of this wonderfull Conflagration, and to do in four dayes what four Armies of Enemies (not oppoſed) could ſcarce have done in eight. The Aſtrologers, whoſe ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is as abſtruſe as uncertain, would fain introduce another cauſe between the firſt and the ſecond, to wit, the poſition and influence of the Coeleſtial bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies; but this accident will contribute much to ſtop their mouthes: for either they could not foreſee it, or elſe having foreſeen it, they ſhould have given us praecaution of it, as they do of many other more frivolous things, and of leſs conſequence then this; and which are never true but by a ſuppoſition that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> doe not happen in our Countrey, they may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="11" facs="tcp:96059:8"/>Let us therefore conclude, that the two Cauſes above mentioned, that is, firſt and ſecond, are ſufficient to move us to humble our ſelves in the ſight of God, who having the year before deſtroyed in the ſpace of Six moneths about an Hundred thouſand people; and ſeeing our impenitent hearts and ſeared conſciences return again to our firſt vomiting, of Pride, Drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Swearing, Falſe dealings, Whoring, Treachery, and other vices; after he hath taken away the health of ſome, he taketh away the wealth of others, and threatneth the reſt with an impendent Famine by the laſt exceſſive Rains he did ſend, and may ſend again in this Sowing-time; and it will avail nothing here to ſay, as I have heard many, that other Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, as <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Italy</hi> are guilty of as many if not greater Crimes then we are, ſeeing that God cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſeth every ſon he loveth, and that he beginneth his Judgements by his own houſhold, and this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion having received more proſperities and bleſſings from his hands then any other, and accordingly more peculiarly bound to ſerve and obey him then all the reſt, whom he will find well enough when he ſeeth his due appointed time: <hi>For that ſervant that knew his lords will and prepared not himſelf, neither did ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his will, ſhall be beaten with many ſtripes; but he that knew not and did commit things worthy of ſtripes, ſhall be heaten with few ſtripes: For unto whom much is given, of him ſhall be much required, and to whom men have committed much, of him they will ask the more.</hi> Luke, ch. 12. v. 47, 48.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:96059:9"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Quid?</hi> What hath he done? <hi>SECT.</hi> II.</head>
                  <p>THE Anſwer is eaſie. An Incendie, a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flagration, a Ruine and devaſtation by Fire, ſuch (as I believe) did never happen by any natural and ordinary means, for that of <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah</hi> was ſupernatural and miraculous, the like being ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver heard before nor after, that it ſhould rain Fire and Brimſtone ſuddenly, and in ſuch a quantity in fair weather; for the Scripture mentioneth that the Sun was riſen upon the Earth, beſides, that inſtead of calcining the ſaid Towns into powder, as Fire and Brimſtone will do all ſolid bodies, it not onely turned them, but alſo the ground on which they ſtood into a bottomleſs bituminous Lake, which to this day remaineth before our eyes for a fearfull Example of the hainouſneſs of Sinne, and of the ſeverity of God's Juſtice. Concerning the confla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gration of <hi>Troy,</hi> and that of <hi>Rome:</hi> The firſt may be fabulous, or exagerated by the familiar Hyper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boles of Poets to whoſe relation chiefly we owe our belief in that point. As for that of <hi>Rome</hi> it is to be believed, that thoſe heaps of Stones and Marbles of which ſhe was then builded, gave a great check, if not a ſtop to the raging of the Fire, and ſtood in the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:96059:9"/>way of the Tyrants pleaſure. Concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing others, as that of<note n="(a)" place="margin">Turkiſh His ſtory.</note> 
                     <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi>
                     <note n="(b)" place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> Cromen.</note> 
                     <hi>Cracow,</hi>
                     <note n="(c)" place="margin">Paulus Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vius <hi>12</hi> Book.</note> 
                     <hi>Venice,</hi>
                     <note n="(d)" place="margin">Cuſomion in vita Emp.</note> 
                     <hi>Vienna</hi> in <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtria,</hi>
                     <note n="(e)" place="margin">Ad Junius.</note> 
                     <hi>Delf</hi> in <hi>Holland,</hi>
                     <note n="(f)" place="margin">Guicciard <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>12</hi> Book.</note> 
                     <hi>Malines</hi> and <hi>Antwerp,</hi> they came nothing near this which in three dayes and three nights of about 460 acres of Ground up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which the City of <hi>London</hi> ſtood, hath ſwept away about 350, which is at the rate of four parts in five, having deſtroyed about 12000 Houſes, 87 Parochial Churches, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides 6 or 7 conſecrated Chappels, and the magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficent and ſtately Cathedral Church of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> the publick and moſt excellent buildings of the <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change, Guildhall, Cuſtom-houſe,</hi> and all or very near the Halls belonging to every private Company, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides an innumerable quantity of Goods of all ſorts, this City being the beſt Magazin not onely of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> but alſo of all <hi>Europe;</hi> but amongſt the reſt it was a Treaſure unſpeakable of four Commodities, which for their luggage and cumberſomneſs, could not be reſcued from the jaws of that unmercifull Element, that is Wine, Tobacco, Spices and Books. As for Books, the Bookſellers who dwelled for the moſt part round about the Cathedral Church, had ſheltered their Books in a ſubterraneal Church un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Cathedral, called St. <hi>Faiths,</hi> which was prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up with ſo ſtrong an Arch and maſſy Pillars, that it ſeemed impoſſible the Fire could do any harm to it; but the Fire having crept into it through the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:96059:10"/>Windows, it ſeized upon the Pews, and did ſo try and examine the Arch and Pillars by ſucking the moyſture of the morter that bound the Stones to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, that it was calcined into Sand: So that when the top of the Cathedral fell upon it, it beat it flat, and ſet all things in an irremediable flame. I have heard judicious men of that Trade affirm, that the onely loſſe of Books in that place, and <hi>Stationers-hall,</hi> publick Libraries, and private per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons Houſes, could amount to no leſs than 150000 pound. I have ſeen Bells, and Iron Wares melted, Glaſs and Earthen pots melted together, as it had been by a fire or fuſion; the moſt bigg and ſolid Stones (as thoſe of the Cathedral) ſlit, ſcaled, and in ſome parts calcined to powder by the violence of the frames. Nevertheleſs, as Gods mercy is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all his works, and remembereth it alwayes amongſt his judgements, I could not learn of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove half a dozen People that did periſh by that wofull Conflagration; one of them was of my Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance, and a Watch-maker living in <hi>Shooe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lane</hi> behinde the Globe-Tavern, his name was <hi>Paul Lawell,</hi> born in <hi>Strasbourg,</hi> who being about 80 years of age, and dull of hearing, was alſo deaf to the good admonitions of his Sonne and Friends, and would neyer deſert the Houſe till it fell upon him, and ſunk him with the ruines, in the Cellar, where afterwards his Bones, together with his Keys, were found.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:96059:10"/>Although the loſs of ſo famous a CITY, and of the Riches contained within its Precinct be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtimable, nevertheleſs to ſatisfie the curioſity of the Reader, and that of Poſterity, as alſo to give ſome light unto thoſe, who, with a more mature deliberation, ſhall attempt the full Hiſtory of it; we will ſet down the chiefeſt Heads by which it is valued, leaving the liberty to the judicions Reader to adde to or ſubſtract from as he ſhall think fit; for we do not pretend here to give an exact account of all the Loſſes, which we hope ſome better, Witts, and that are more at leaſure, will undertake here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, But onely to invite them by this to a more curious and earneſt enquiry of the Truth, and ſo tranſmit to Poſterity a fearfull Example of God's Judgement, that they may in avoiding Sinne, alſo avoid the like, to the glory and prayſe of his moſt holy Name.</p>
                  <p>Let it therefore be ſaid again, that by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of the beſt Geometricians, the City of <hi>LONDON</hi> within the Walls was ſeated upon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 460 Acres of Ground, wherein were built a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 15000 Houſes, beſides Churches, Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pels, Schools, Halls, and publick Buildings; out of this quantity of Houſes 12000 are thought to be burnt, which is four parts of five, each Houſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing valued one with another at Twenty five pound a years Rent, which at Twelve years Purchaſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth Three hundred pound, the whole <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="16" facs="tcp:96059:11"/>
                     <table>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Fourſcore and ſeven Parochial Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, beſides that of St. <hi>Pauls</hi> the Cathedral, and ſix conſecrated Cliappels, the <hi>Exchange, Guildhall, Cuſtome-houſe,</hi> the Halls of Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, and other Publick Buildings, amounting to half as much</cell>
                           <cell>1800000 <hi>l.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>The Goods that every Private man loſt one with another, valued at half the value of the Houſes</cell>
                           <cell>1800000 <hi>l.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>About 20 Wharſes of Coals and Wood, valued at a 1000 <hi>l.</hi> a piece</cell>
                           <cell>20000 <hi>l.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>About 100000 Boats and Barges, 1000 Cart-loads, with Porters to remove the Goods to and fro, as well for the Houſes that were a burning, as for thoſe that ſtood in fear of it, at 20 ſhillings a Load</cell>
                           <cell>150000 <hi>l.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Summe</cell>
                           <cell>7335000 <hi>l.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
                  <p>This being reduced to the Account of <hi>French</hi>-Money, taking one pound Sterling for 13 Livers, amounteth to 10569675000 Livers.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:96059:11"/>Now O <hi>London!</hi> it may well be ſaid of thee, <hi>How doth the city ſit ſolitary that was full of people, how is ſhe become widow, ſhe that was great among the Nations, and Princeſs among the Provinces?</hi> Jerem. Lam. chap. 1.1. But courage O thou that art now my Countrey, thou art fallen into the hands of God and not of men; he that chaſtiſeth thee is thy Father, and if he hath a rod to puniſh thee, he hath alſo a ſtaff to comfort thee, turn to him and he will turn to thee, for he is a merciful, long-ſuffering, not willing that any ſhould periſh, but that all ſhould come to repentance, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be not overwhelmed with ſorrow, no thing hath befallen thee, but hath happened to others before thee; and if it be true that the likeneſs and partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation of afflictions doth mitigate the ſenſe of them, that I may ſomething allay thy preſent ſorrow, I will relate thee a ſtory that hath much parallel with thine, to ſhew thou haſt not been the onely miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: It is a true one, written and teſtified by an Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable <hi>Dutch</hi> Merchant who was an eye witneſs to it; and although it hath been once printed, yet becauſe the Book is ſcarce, and the Language forrain, I thought thou wouldſt not take it ill if I ſhould impart it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Moſcow</hi> the chief City of all the Countreys of the Emperour of <hi>Ruſsia,</hi> is a very great City, but not well compacted, it hath in compaſs with the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urbs, well inhabited, and as full of people as the Town, about three <hi>German</hi> leagues and a half, which maketh about 14 <hi>Engliſh</hi> miles; the compaſs of the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:96059:12"/>Town within the walls is about three <hi>Engliſh</hi> miles; the ſtreets and path ways are of great trees ſet cloſe together, and ſome boards by the houſes ſide; and it is ſo dirty in rainy weather, that it is impoſſible to go thorow the City otherwiſe then on horſe-back; according to the cuſtom of the Countrey where horſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es are of ſmall value, and of little expence, never be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſhod for any journey whatſoever, unleſs it be du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Ice. The houſes are but one ſtory high, or two at the moſt, all built with wood ſet up at the top one of another; there is in the City, Suburbs and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtel about 5500 Churches, built for the moſt part like Chappels, moſt of them, with great trees ſet one upon another; The great Dukes Lodging is alſo built of wood, which he thinketh wholſomer then ſtone; the Caſtle is pretty well fortified with walls and broad ditches; it occupieth as much room as all the reſt of the City. On one ſide of it dwells the <hi>Sins,</hi> on the other the <hi>Optiſins,</hi> who are as the Treaſurers of the Great Duk, in whoſe hands (as ſoon as you come) you muſt put in all your Merchandiſes; Being depart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from <hi>Nerva</hi> about the tenth of <hi>July</hi> 1570. we came on the beginning of <hi>Auguſt</hi> to <hi>Moſcow,</hi> where I found the Great Duke and his Officers buſie in ſeeking out about 30 perſons,<note place="margin">This Great Duke was <hi>John Baſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clides</hi> the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Tyrant.</note> who fell all under the ſword of the Hangman, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept one who was caſt alive in boiling wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and this becauſe they had taken Bribes, moſt of them were great Lords, and Familiars with the Great Duke, others were Merchants of <hi>Nouogard,</hi> with their
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:96059:12"/>Wives Children and Families, accuſed of Treaſon in the behalf of the King of <hi>Poland.</hi> Few days after, a horrid Plague invaded the town of <hi>Moſcow,</hi> and the places about it, with ſuch violence, that in four months there died above 250000 people, and it was particularly obſerved that in eight days, that is, from the tenth to the eighteenth of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> there died 2703 Prieſts, and this Plague did continue ſo fiercely, that in the end of it, every one wondered when he met any body of his acquaintance.</p>
                  <p>This extraordinary miſery was ſo lowed the year after on the fifteenth of <hi>May,</hi> by a ſtrange ruine and conflagration; the occaſion was, that the Emperour of the <hi>Tartarians,</hi> being diſcontented that the <hi>Ruſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians</hi> did not pay him ſome annual Tribute, and hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing beſides that the Great Duke by his tyranny and maſſacres had ſo depopulated the Countrey, that he ſhould find no great reſiſtance that way, did ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon him to pay the ſaid Tribute, but the Great Duke returned nothing in anſwer but ſpightful and reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful words; wherefore the <hi>Tartarian</hi> came out of his Countrey about the end of <hi>February,</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed with an Army of 100000 horſe, who with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the ſpace of two moneths and a half did ride a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 500 <hi>German</hi> leagues which makes 2000 <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſt</hi> miles; when they were come about two days journey from the frontiers of the Duke, he reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to meet them and to give them battle, but he loſt it with a prodigious ſlaughter of his men; The Duke knowing that the <hi>Tartarian</hi> would ſeek
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:96059:13"/>him out, ran away as faſt and as far as he could; he was only within nine leagues of <hi>Moſcow,</hi> when the <hi>Tartarians</hi> came and encompaſſed the Town, thinking he was within, they ſet a fire all the Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lages round about it, and ſeeing that the war would prove too tedious for them, reſolved to burn that great City, or at leaſt the Suburbs of it; for this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe having placed their Troops round about it, they ſet fire on all ſides, ſo that it ſeemed a burning Globe; then did ariſe ſo fierce and violent a wind, that it drove the Rafters and long Trees from the Suburbs into the City; the conſlagration was ſo ſuddain that no body had time to ſave himſelf but in that place where he was then; the perſons that were burnt in this fire were above 200000. which did happen, becauſe the houſes are all of wood, and the ſtreets paved with great Firr-trees ſet cloſe toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which being Oily and Roſinous made the incen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die unexpreſſible, ſo that in four hours time, the City and Suburbs were wholly conſumed. I and a young man of <hi>Rochel</hi> that was my Interpreter, were in the middle of the Fire, in a Magazine vaulted with ſtone, and extraordinarily ſtrong, whoſe wall was three foot and a half thick, and had no Air but on two ſides, one wherein was the coming in and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out, which was a long Alley, in which there was three iron Gates, diſtant about ſix foot one from another; on the other ſide there was a Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow or Grate, fenced with three iron ſhutters, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant half a foot one from another, we ſhut them
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:96059:13"/>inwardly as well as poſſibly we could; nevertheleſs, there came in ſo much ſmoak, that it was more then ſufficient to choak us, had it not been for ſome Beer that was there, with the which we refreſhed our ſelves now and then. Many Lords and Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men were ſtifled in the Caves where they had reti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, becauſe their houſes being made of great trees, when they fell they cruſhed down all that was under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath; others being conſumed to aſhes, ſtopt all the paſſages of going and coming out, ſo that for want of Air they all periſhed. The poor Countrey peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that had ſaved themſelves in the City, with their Cattel from Threeſcore miles round about, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the conflagration, ran all into the Market-place. which is not paved of wood as the reſt; neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs they were all roſted there, in ſuch ſort that the talleſt man ſeemed but a child, ſo much had the fire contracted their Limbs, and this by reaſon of the great houſes that were round about; a thing more hideous and frightful then any can imagine. In many places of the ſaid Market, the bodies were piled one upon another to the heighth of half a pike, which put me into a wonderful admiration, being not able to apprehend nor underſtand, how it was poſſible they ſhould be ſo heaped together.</p>
                  <p>This wonderful conflagration cauſed all the Forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications of the Town wall to fall; and all the Ordnance that were upon it to burſt. The walls were made of Brick, according to the ancient way of building,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:96059:14"/>without either Fortifications or Ditches; many that had ſaved themſelves along them, were neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs roſted, ſo fierce and vehement was the fire, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them many <hi>Italians</hi> and <hi>Walloons</hi> of my ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance; while the fire laſted, we thought that a million of Cannons had been thundering together, and our thoughts were upon nothing but death, thinking that the fire would laſt ſome days, becauſe of the great circumference of the Caſtle and Suburbs; but all this was done in leſs then four hours time, at the end of which, the noiſe growing leſs, we were curious to know whether the <hi>Tartarians,</hi> of whom we ſtood in no leſs fear then of the fire, were en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred. They are a Warlike people, though they eat nothing but Roots, and ſuch other like ſubſtance, and drink onely Water. The greateſt Lords among them feed upon Fleſh baked between a Horſe and the Saddle, wherein rideth the Horſeman: neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs are they very ſtrong, luſty, and inured to all hardſhip, as alſo are their Horſes, who are wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſwift, and will travel further in one day, eating nothing but Graſs, then ours will do in three feeding upon Oats; therefore the <hi>Tartarians</hi> come ſo eaſily from ſo far to invade the <hi>Ruſſians.</hi> They have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo that craft, that they onely come in the Summer for the conveniency of their horſes; their Countrey is temperate, from whence they come about the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter end of <hi>February,</hi> that they may be in <hi>Ruſſia</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the beginning of <hi>June,</hi> and go back again in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their own countrey at the end of it, leaſt they
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:96059:14"/>ſhould be overtaken by the winter in <hi>Ruſſia,</hi> which if i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſhould fall out they would be all ſtarved be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the great deſerts uninhabited, containing above Three hundred <hi>German</hi> leagues, and therefore void of all relief, as well for themſelves as for their horſes, there being then no graſs upon the ground, which conſtraineth them to make ſuch a journey, which is of above 1200 <hi>German</hi> leagues in four or five months time with all their Army, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth commonly of about 150000 or 200000 horſes as good as can be, but the horſemen are but ſlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly armed, having for all weapons a jack of Mail, a Dart, and Bowe and Arrows, they know nothing of what belongeth to Guns, having in all heir Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey but Two Cities, wherein the Emperor keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his Court, without any Villages or Houſes, but are contented to live under Tents, which they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move to and fro as they ſee occaſion.</p>
                  <p>But to come again to our Miſery, after we had hearkened a while, we hard ſome <hi>Ruſſians</hi> running to and fro through the ſmoak, who were talking of walling the Gates to prevent the coming in of the <hi>Tartarians,</hi> who were expecting when the fire went out. I and my Interpreter being come out of the Magazine, found the Aſhes ſo hot that we durſt ſcarce tread upon them, but neceſſity compelling us we ran towards the chief Gate, where we found Twenty five or Thirty men eſcaped from the fire, with whom in few hours we did wall that Gate and the reſt,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:96059:15"/>and kept a ſtrict watch all that night with ſome Guns that had been preſerved from the fire. In the morning, ſeeing that the place was not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſible with ſo few people as we were, we ſought the means to get into the Caſtle, whoſe entry was then inacceſſible; the Governour was ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry glad to hear of our intention, and cryed to us, we ſhould be very welcom, but it was a moſt difficult thing to come in, becauſe the Bridges were all burnt, ſo that we were fain to get over the wall, having inſtead of Ladders ſome high Firr-trees thrown from the Caſtle to us, wherein inſtead of rounds to get up, they had made ſome notches with a hatchet to keep us from ſliding: we got up then with much adoe; for beſides the evident inconveniency of thoſe rough Ladders, we did carry about us the ſum of 4000 Thalers, beſides ſome Jewels, which was a great hindrance to us to climb along thoſe high trees, and that which did double our fear was, that we ſaw before our eyes ſome of our company, that had nothing but their bodies to ſave, yet tumble down from the middle of thoſe high trees into the Ditch, full of burnt bodies, ſo that we could not tread but upon dead corpſes, whoſe helps were ſo thick every where, that we could not avoid to tread upon them, as if it had been a hill to climb up, and that which did augment our trouble was, that in treading upon them, the Arms and Legs broke like Glaſs; the poor Limbs of theſe Creatures being calcined by the vehement heat of the fire, and our feet ſink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:96059:15"/>into thoſe miſerable bodies, the bloud and the filth did ſquirt in our faces, which begot ſuch a ſtench all the Town over that it impoſſible to ſubſiſt in it.</p>
                  <p>The 25th of <hi>May</hi> in the evening, as we expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in great perplexity what the <hi>Tartarians</hi> would attempt againſt us who were about Four hundred in the Caſtle: the <hi>Tartarians</hi> whom we had ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with our Guns, and killed ſome of them that were come too neer one of the Caſtle-gates, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to go back the ſame way that they came in, with ſo much ſpeed, that the next morning all that torrent was drained up, for which having gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven God thanks and ſet our buſineſs in order, as well as the preſent calamity would permit, we went away from that deſolate place.</p>
                  <p>Now O <hi>London!</hi> conſider that thy Fate is not peculiar to thy ſelf, and that will allay the bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of thy ſufferings; Remember alſo, that if thou ſanctifieſt this affliction to thy uſe, the Lord pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth by his Prophet, <hi>that thoſe ſhall reap in joy who did ſow in tears,</hi> Pſal. 126.6.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:96059:16"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi? <hi>Where?</hi>
                     </hi> SECT. III.</head>
                  <p>IN the richeſt City of <hi>Europe,</hi> and perhaps of the world; the greateſt Magazine that could be found for all ſorts of Merchandiſes, incompara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for the ſalubritie of the Air, and convenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of ſcituation; Magnificent in publique buildings; Illuſtrious in good deeds, Renowned for Hoſpitali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Famous for government, Venerable for anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity; having ſubſiſted about Two thouſand years; inhabited by Citizens whoſe courage was equal to their fortunes; in a word, a City of which it might be ſaid more truly then of <hi>Ormus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Si terrarum orbis quaqua patet annulus eſſet;</l>
                     <l>Londinum illius gemma decusque foret.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>This circumſtance which we tread over ſo ſlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that we may not be ſuſpected of flattery, is not the leaſt that aggravateth the enormity of this accident, there is none of thoſe characters we have given it, but is very true, and might be the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy employment of a better penn then mine, and the ſubject of a full volume.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:96059:16"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Quibus auxiliis? <hi>By whoſe help?</hi>
                     </hi> SECT. IV.</head>
                  <p>HEre we muſt have recourſe to what we have ſaid before in the firſt Paragrapht, when we ſpoke of the ſecond cauſes, and ſay that God hath made uſe chiefly of eight things to accompliſh this work. The negligence of the Maſter or his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, in whoſe houſe the fire did firſt begin; the ſolitarineſs of the night, the narrowneſs of the place, the weakneſs of the buildings, the quantity of combuſtible and bituminous matters gathered thereabout, the preceding Summer which was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinarily hot and dry, the <hi>Eaſt</hi> wind that blew violently all that while, and the want of Engines and water to quench the fire; we ſhall give every one his little Section, to ſatisfie the curioſity of theſe, who inquire ſo much of the cauſes that have made this conflagration ſo violent, diſmal and irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediable.</p>
                  <p n="1">I. Though there be ſome accidents which no humane prudence can prevent; as when a man ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in his own houſe, or going through the ſtreet, is craſhed by a ſudden ruine; nevertheleſs the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers are not to blame, when they ſay that
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:96059:17"/>every one may be the author of his own fortune, for it is certain, that if a man neglecteth or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaketh that providence given him by nature, he doth together forſake the inſtrument and the means which his good genius maketh uſe of to make him avoid the ill accidents that may befall him, for as our ſoul doth only act by the Organs of our body, ſo our Genius either good or bad cannot act but by the means of our ſoul; now if our ſoul enjoyeth a ſound and temperate body, and doth her functions with purity and facility; that Genius which is always neer hand, and as it were whiſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at our ear, doth move and ſtirr her to the preſervation of whatſoever belongeth or concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth her: if on the contrary, this ſoul inhabiteth a body dyſcratiated, melanchollick, full of obſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, or drowned in the exceſſes of eating and drinking, or paſſions, its nature being igneous, and never ceaſing from action; it neceſſarily followeth, that according to the diſpoſition of the Organes, ſhe turneth to the wrong way and neglecteth thoſe things wherein ſhe is meerly concerned. Now in things that might be prevented or remedied, it is an invalid excuſe to ſay, I would never have thought that ſuch thing ſhould happen. For who can attribute it to a meer accident to put fire in an Oven, and to leave quantity of dry wood, and ſome flitches of Bacon by it within the ſphaere of its activity, and ſo go to bed, in leaving his provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence with his ſlippers.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="29" facs="tcp:96059:17"/>I remember that ſome 36 years ago, in a Town of <hi>Brie,</hi> a Province of <hi>France,</hi> called <hi>Sezane,</hi> upon a Sunday morning, a Woman that kept a Chandlers ſhop having occaſion to ſnuff a Candle, threw the ſnuff into a corner of her ſhop among ſome old rags and papers, and ſo ſhutting the door went to <hi>Maſs,</hi> but within the ſpace of half an hour, and before ſhe could come back again, not only her houſe, but thoſe of her Neighbours were all in a flame, which being helped by an Eaſt-wind which blew at that time, and which is the moſt dangerous of all the Winds for Incendies, (as we ſhall ſhew hereafter) did in the ſpace of a day and a night conſume the whole Town, conſiſting of about four hundred hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. Can this be called a meer accident, ſince there is no body ſo void of common ſenſe but might have either foreſeen, or prevented ſo calamitous a conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence?</p>
                  <p n="2">II. The ſecond cauſe of this misfortune is the time wherein it did happen, to wit, about one of the clock in the night, when every one is buried in his firſt ſleep; when ſome for wearineſs, others by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boiſtneſs, have given leave to their cares to retire; when ſlothfulneſs and the heat of the bed have rivet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a man to his Pillow, and made him almoſt incapable of waking, much leſs of acting and helping his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours.</p>
                  <p n="3">III. The narrowneſs of the place did alſo much
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:96059:18"/>contribute to this Conflagration, for the Street where it did happen, as alſo moſt of thoſe about it, were the narroweſt of the City, inſomuch that in ſome a Cart could ſcarce go along, and in others not at all. The danger I did once run of my life thereabouts by the crowd of Carts, hath cauſed me many times to make reflexion on the covetouſneſs of the Citizens, and connivency of Magiſtrates, who have ſuffered them from time to time to encroach upon the ſtreets, and ſo to jet the top of their hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, ſo as from one ſide of the ſtreet to touch the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which as it doth facilitate a conflagration, ſo doth it alſo hinder the remedy, and beſides taketh away the liberty of the air, making it unwhole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, and disfigureth the Beauty and Symmetry of the City. I hope that for the future his Majeſty, his Councel, and that of the City, will take care that ſuch diſorder happen no more, and will cauſe this City to be as commodious in its Buildings, as it is happy in its Scituation.</p>
                  <p n="4">IV. Now followeth the weakneſs of the build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, which were almoſt all of wood, which by age was grown as dry as a chip: This inconvenient will eaſily be remedied, in building the houſes with Stone or Brick, according to the Statutes and Ordinances of Parliament provided and Enacted long ago in that behalf, though for the moſt part ill obſerved.</p>
                  <p n="5">V. The quantity of combuſtible and bituminous
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:96059:18"/>matter hath given the greateſt encouragement to this devouring Fire; for as the place where the fire be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun was not far from the <hi>Thames,</hi> and from thoſe Wharfes where moſt Merchandiſes are landed, ſo <hi>Thames-ſtreet,</hi> and others thereabout, were almoſt nothing elſe but Magazines of combuſtible and ſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phurous Merchandiſes: Thereabout were a prodigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous quantity of Oyl, Butter, Brandy, Pitch, Brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, Saltpeter, Cables, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and by the <hi>Thames</hi> ſide were almoſt all Wharfes full of Coals and Wood. Now as fire of it ſelf is nothing but light which corporifieth it ſelf in the matter, and acteth more or leſs according to the diſpoſition of it, as we ſee that a fire of Straw is leſs violent than that of Coals; it followeth that this fire having lighted upon theſe ſulphureous and bituminous matters, did feed upon them as in his proper Element, and not only devou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red them with eaſe, but imparts to the next combu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtible matters a diſpoſition more fitting and apt to receive him. The Nature of this ſulphureous fire was evidently ſeen in the melting of Bells, Iron, Pots, Glaſſes, and other metallique things, and in the calcining of ſtones and bricks, which no other ſingle fire of wood, coals, or other vulgar matter could have done. I remember that ſome four or five years ago the Lightning fell in <hi>Herefordſhire</hi> without doing any harm in the Country, but being extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed of it ſelf, the exhalation of it did mix it ſelf with a ſtrong Weſterly wind, that came as far as <hi>London,</hi> beating down houſes, plucking up trees by
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:96059:19"/>the roots; and to ſhew its nitrous and ſulphureous Nature, did as it were neglect to touch wood, but did chiefly ſtick upon metal, and either broke or bended it; the tokens of it are ſeen to this day up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Steeples of <hi>Bowchurch,</hi> St. <hi>Andrew,</hi> St. <hi>Giles Cripplegate,</hi> the <hi>May-Pole,</hi> and other places. Theſe ſulphureous matters were alſo the cauſe of another inconveniency, which is, that the fire being corpori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in them, did extend the ſphaere of his activity at a further diſtance then ordinary, and caſt his burning beams furtheſt off, mixing more exactly his Atomes in the Air, which he turneth almoſt into his own Nature, which was the cauſe that no body could come neerer that fire then a hundred or two hundred paces.</p>
                  <p n="6">VI. The foregoing Summer that was extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naryly hot and dry, had alſo diſpoſed the matter of the buildings to admit the fire more quickly and eaſily, by ſucking not only the intrinſecal moiſture that was in them, but alſo that of the Air which might have moiſtned them; for though there be no rain falling, nevertheleſs there is a certain evapouriſh moiſture in the Air, which if it be not dried up, doth moiſten all porous things intrinſecally, and doth condenſe it ſelf upon the ſolid ones, in the form of an Oleaginous moiſture, as doth appear upon Marbles and Glaſſes.</p>
                  <p n="7">VII. In cometh now the Eaſt-wind to play his part in this Tragedy. That unfortunate wind, of
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:96059:19"/>which it is commonly ſaid, that it is neither good for man nor beaſt, did blow with ſuch a wonderful fierce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs all the time of the conflagration, that it did not only quicken the fire, as Bellows do the Furnaces, but alſo getting into the ſtreets, and among the houſes, when it found any let or hinderance that did recoil it back, it blew equally both to the right and to the left, and cauſed the fire to burn on all ſides, which hath perſwaded many that this fire was mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous: I my ſelf remember, that going into ſome ſtreets at that time, and having the wind impetuouſly in my face, I was in hope that at my return I ſhould have it in my back, but it was all one, for the reaſon aforeſaid. It would be here too tedious to ſpeak of the nature of winds, and to ſhew many reaſons why this wind is ſo dry in <hi>England,</hi> as to burn the flowers and leafs of the trees, more then the hotteſt Sun can do, one which I think ſatisfactory will ſerve for all: It is therefore to be obſerved, that winds do not only participate of the nature of the places where they are begot, but alſo of that of the Countries tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough which they paſs: Now all the <hi>Southern, We<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtern,</hi> and <hi>Northern</hi> winds, muſt paſs thorough the great Ocean to come into <hi>England,</hi> in which paſſage there mixes with them abundance of vapours which cauſe their moiſture, except the <hi>North</hi>-wind, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the moiſture is condenſed by the cold; but the <hi>Eaſt</hi>-wind to come to us muſt paſs over the greateſt Continent of the world, <hi>France, Germany, Hunga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Greece, Perſia, &amp;c.</hi> even to <hi>China;</hi> ſo that in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſing ſuch a tract of Land, it not only droppeth
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:96059:20"/>down by the way his moiſt Effluviums, the earth as it were ſucking them for its irroration, but alſo carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth along all the hot and dry exhalations that perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually ariſe out of the earth, which is the cauſe of his dry and burning quality. I had formerly a little Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, where I did beſtow as much pains and cares as I could, to bring up ſome young Fruit-trees that were in't, having the advantage of a very good mould, but being ſeated <hi>Eaſtward</hi> and cloſed narrowly by a Brick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wall on either ſide; this wind that raigneth conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly here in <hi>England</hi> in the moneths of <hi>March, April</hi> and beginning of <hi>May,</hi> did in their budding ſo burn the leaves and the flowers, that the hotteſt Sun could not do the like, ſo that I was fain to give it o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, having been two or three years before I could underſtand that myſtery, and the nature of that wind in this countrey, for there is ſome other countreys where this wind is ſalubrious and fruitful enough.</p>
                  <p n="8">VIII. It was alſo a great contributing to this miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune, that the <hi>Thames</hi> Water-houſe was out of order, ſo that the Conduits and Pipes were almoſt all dry; as alſo that the Engines had no liberty to play, for the narrowneſs of the place and crowd of the people, but ſome of them were tumbled down in the river, and among the reſt, that of <hi>Clearken-well,</hi> eſteemed one of the beſt.</p>
                  <p>And thus courteous Reader, thou ſeeſt an admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble concurrence of ſeveral cauſes, for the putting of Gods will in execution; in other Cities that are not ſubject to conflagrations; as <hi>Paris,</hi> which is all built of Free-ſtone, the innundations have ſeveral times
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:96059:20"/>played their pranks; other Towns, as in <hi>Italy</hi> that think themſelves exempted from fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e and water, come to their periods by fearful Earthquakes; others that eſcape Fire, Water and Earth, do periſh by the Meteors of the Air, and are calcined by the Lighten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; ſo that God Almighty never wanteth inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to compaſs his will; and it ſeemeth that the four Elements, of which this world is compounded, do conſpire againſt the happineſs and quietneſs of man, when by their daily prevarications they go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to confirm the diſobedience of our firſt Parents.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Cur? <hi>Why?</hi>
                     </hi> SECT. V.</head>
                  <p>HEre it is that we muſt wholly ſtoop and humble our ſelves under the mighty hand of God, and anſwer with the Apoſtle, <hi>O the depth of the riches of the wiſdom and knowledge of God, how unſearchable are his judgements, and his ways paſt finding out! For who hath known the mind of the Lord, or who hath been his Counſellor?</hi> Rom. 11.33. let it ſuffice thee O man to know, that whether he hath done it to puniſh thee for thy ſins, or to try thy Faith and exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe thy Patience; if thou canſt make benefit of this affliction, and ſanctify it to thy uſe; We know that all things work together for good, to them that love God. <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
